<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discovery of the Society in relation to their politicks written originally by a well-wisher to the Jesuits.</title>
            <author>Well-wisher to the Jesuits.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36130</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1659</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5361</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12580667</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12580667</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63736</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36130)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63736)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 960:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discovery of the Society in relation to their politicks written originally by a well-wisher to the Jesuits.</title>
                  <author>Well-wisher to the Jesuits.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63736:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOVERY Of the SOCIETY In relation to their POLITICKS. Written Originally, BY A <hi>Well-wiſher to the JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ITS.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:63736:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63736:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>WEe are by a <hi>Divine</hi> Authority aſſur'd, that there are thoſe in the world, who who <hi>like the deaf Adder,</hi> out of pure obstinacy, <hi>will not hear the voice of the Charmer,</hi> and that there is a generation of men that <hi>hate to be reformed.</hi> Thence is it, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly experience is ſo pregnant to ſhew, that, of all the people, theſe look on the leaſt diſcovery of their enormities, as the moſt hainous injury can be done them; making ſo little advantage either of the charming <hi>Admonitions</hi> of Friends, or the conſorious <hi>Reproaches</hi> of <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> that they think it the greateſt <hi>ſhame</hi> that may be to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract,</hi> and chooſe rather to betray their <hi>exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> then expreſſe any deſires of <hi>amendment.</hi> That the enſuing Piece was written long ſince, and that by a Perſon not much an enemy to the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits,</hi> are things not to be diſſembled, as being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable from ſeverall paſſages of it: but to give a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an account of the preſent revivall of it, is what cannot be done without a certain regret, and compaſſion. <hi>That Religious men,</hi> ſuch as had by ſolemn <hi>Vowes</hi> abjur'd not only the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this world, but alſo all commerce with
<pb facs="tcp:63736:3"/>it, as to what concerns the management of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs thereof, ſhould be guilty of ſo great miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, argues ſuch a grievance, and dereliction of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> that, according to their Justificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they ſhould be guided by, as cannot without horror fall into the reflection of a good man. But to find them ſo wedded to miſchievous practiſes, as that, though they were long ſince lay'd at their doores, there ſhould ſtill be a neceſſity to bring them upon the ſtage, and that meerly becauſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer remonſtrances proved fruitleſſe and ineffectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, it certainly speaks not an <hi>indifference,</hi> or <hi>backwardneſſe,</hi> but a <hi>hatred</hi> of reformation. And yet thus does the caſe ſtand with the <hi>Society,</hi> whoſe courſes gave eccaſion of the preſent DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COVERY.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63736:3"/>
            <head>A DISCOVERY Of the SOCIETY In relation to their POLITICKS, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>UPon the firſt Inſtitution of the <hi>Society</hi> and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Order</hi> of the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> it was generally look'd upon as a <hi>Tree</hi> planted in the Vineyard of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> where of the fruits ſhould be an Antidote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the poiſon of <hi>Hereſy,</hi> and whoſe bloſſoms ſhould be no other then thoſe of Chriſtian and Religious works, for the edification of, and reduction of thoſe ſouls that otherwiſe were likely to ſtray. And ſuch no doubt it was intended by the Founder thereof, <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and ſuch, it is to be thought, continu'd while it was cultivated by thoſe firſt Fathers, from whoſe Piety, and auſterity, as it deriv'd vigour and life, ſo did it ſorce the eſteem and veneration of all. This glorious Tree ſpread it ſelf into two Branches, one of Love towards <hi>God,</hi> the other toward their <hi>Neighbour.</hi> So that conſidering the ſmalneſs of its roots, it is almoſt incredible, what a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of fruit it brought forth, in the excellent edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63736:4"/>of children, the ſaving of ſouls, and the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith.</p>
            <p>But the indefatigable Enemy of Mankind, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, who is exaſperated at all manner of good, and whatſoever hath the leaſt tendency to reformation, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd his earneſtneſs and ſubtilty to deſtroy this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>tree,</hi> and with it all the fruitfull advantages the world expected to reap thereby; taking occaſion even from the greatneſs it ſelf of this Religious Order, and from that admirable improvement which it had made in ſo ſmall a ſpace of time, to pervert the firſt Inſtitution thereof, with artifices, ſycophancy and inſinuation. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of theſe two branches of <hi>Charity</hi> towards <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man,</hi> now utterly dry'd up, he hath engrafted two others, one of <hi>ſelf love,</hi> the other a <hi>ſpirit</hi> minding only the <hi>advantages</hi> of this <hi>World.</hi> Which how great a prejudice it hath prov'd to the Chriſtian Religion in all parts of the world, if that be the deſigne of the preſent <hi>DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COVERY</hi> to demonſtrate. Wherein, I ſpeak it in the preſence of the All-ſeeing. I ſhall not advance any thing out of <hi>paſſion</hi> or <hi>interest,</hi> but that whatever is done, proceeds from an innocent <hi>zeal</hi> to the publick good, and a tenderneſſe to the welfare of the Society it ſelf, as alſo to the end, that <hi>Princes</hi> being acquainted with their <hi>artifices,</hi> may, for the benefit of the people they govern, by timely remedies, prevent and clude them.</p>
            <p>It is therefore to be noted, that the Society of the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> ſpreading and enlarging it ſelf more and more by their undertaking the education of Children (a deſign no doubt acceptable to all Cities and Kingdomes) they accordingly, upon their firſt Inſtitution ſo farre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratiated themſelves with <hi>Princes,</hi> that in a few <hi>years</hi> they diffos'd themſelves ſo far as other <hi>Orders</hi> had done in many <hi>Centuries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This unexpected arrivall to Greatneſs, which ever works a ſtrange alteration in mens minds and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, rais'd in the Succeſſors of <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſuch a high
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63736:4"/>opinion of, and love to their own Society, that vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gloriouſly hence concluding themſelves more bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall to the Church of God, and ſuch as had made a far greater progreſs into the buſineſs of <hi>Reformation</hi> then all other <hi>orders,</hi> they thought it their main concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to endeavour it's further growth and enlargement, that is, (to give it you in their own words) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> the <hi>advantages</hi> of his <hi>Church,</hi> and to improve the Patrimony of Jeſus.</p>
            <p>And here can I not but wiſh my ſelf the ſubtilty of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and the eloquence of the Romane Orator to diſcover and expreſs the miraculous wayes whereby they effect their deſign (a thing that by reaſon of its novelty ſeems incredible) and daily enlarge the juriſdiction of their Society. But I ſhall think it ſufficient to glance only at ſome few things, leaving it to other mens judgements to make what gloſſes they ſhall think fitt thereupon, and to conceive an Idea of thoſe men ſuitable thereto. The enſuing heads therefore I deſire the Reader to take for the ground of his diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>The Fathers of the Society finding that their teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, preaching, adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and other religious and Monaſticall exerciſes contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not ſo much as was expected to the raiſing of them to the greatneſſe they aſpired to, were forc'd to think of other wayes to effect their deſign. For though (as is ſaid) they were entertain'd at the beginning with all kindneſs by many people, yet in proceſs of time they perceived that, through diſſatisfaction, or ſome other occaſion, thoſe that had honour'd them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>before withdrew their affection from them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fearing their growth ſhould determine in their infancy, they found out two other wayes to keep up, and to enlarge the greatneſſe of their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:63736:5"/>
            <p>One was, by calumnies and crafty inſinuations to raiſe in the minds of <hi>Princes,</hi> and conſequently as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others as they could, a baſe opinion of all other <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Inſtitutions,</hi> making them deſpicable by diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their imperſections, and like ſubtill <hi>Politicians,</hi> building up their own greatneſſe upon the ruines of others. By this means got they our of the hands of the lawfull Poſſeſſors, many Monaſteries, Abbeys and other Spirituall revenues, depriving thoſe Religious men that formerly enjoy'd them, both of them, and all that belonged thereto.</p>
            <p>Another was, their pragmaticall engaging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Affairs of <hi>State,</hi> thruſting themſelves into the intereſts and concernments of Chriſtian Princes. To bring this to effect, they have as ſubtill and artificious a device as any the world was yet acquainted withall; into which, as it is hard to penetrate, ſo is it almoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to make a ſull diſcovery thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rome</hi> is the conſtant reſidence of the chief of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, commonly known by the name of <hi>General,</hi> or <hi>Pather Generall,</hi> to whom all the reſt render exact obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Beſides him, there are for the moſt part reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the ſame place certain perſons choſen from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the other Fathers, who from the Aſſiſtance they alwayes give Him, are called his <hi>ASSISTANTS.</hi> Of this quality there is one at leaſt as a Repreſentative of every Nation, who, from the Nation he repreſents, takes his name. Hence, one is ſtiled the <hi>Aſſiſtant</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> another of <hi>Spaine,</hi> a third of <hi>Italy,</hi> a fourth of <hi>England,</hi> a fift of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and ſo of all Provinces and Kingdoms. Their main buſineſs is, to give the <hi>F. General</hi> an account of all Occurrences of State in thoſe Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Kingdoms whereof they are the reſpective <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants.</hi> This they perform by the means of their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondents, who, upon that deſign, have their reſiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the principall Cities of the Provinces and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; where they are. And theſe are perpetually ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling up and down to inform themſelves of the State,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63736:5"/>quality, nature, inclination and intentions of Princes, and take advantage of all opportunities to advertiſe the <hi>Aſſiſtants</hi> of ſuch accidents as they have diſcovered. Theſe no ſooner receive them, but they disburthen themſelves of all into the boſom of the Father <hi>Generall,</hi> who thereupon calling his <hi>Aſſiſtants</hi> to Councell, they do as it were anatomiſe the whole world, comparing and ballancing the intereſts, concernments and deſigns of all Chriſtian Princes. Here they conſult of all freſh intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence receiv'd from their Correſpondents, and curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly examining and conferring them together, it is at laſt reſolv'd, that the affairs of ſuch a Prince ſhall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted, the deſigns of another oppos'd as they ſhall conceive moſt for their intereſt and advantage. And as it is poſſible, that the ſtander by may better ſee the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of a Plot, then the Gameſter employ'd in it; ſo is it likely, that the Fathers of the Society taking as it were a generall view of the intereſts of all Princes, are the better able to obſerve the circumſtances of place and time, and effectually advance the Affairs of that Prince who is likely to prove the greateſt favourer of them.</p>
            <p>It is certainly a thing evil in it ſelf and inſuppertable, that a ſort of men devoted to a Religious life, ſhould ſo much inter meddle with matters of State, it being their duty to provide for the welfare of ſouls, as ſuch as had to that end taken leave of the concernments of the world. But it is to be conſidered, that the Fathers of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, are, as to this point, more intangled then thoſe who have the management thereof, and for many pernicious conſequences ariſing thereby, this procedure of theirs will be found moſt miſchievous, and conſequently ſuch as requires a ſpeedy and effectuall remedy.</p>
            <p>For, in the firſt place, the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are <hi>Confeſſors</hi> to the greateſt part of the <hi>Nobility</hi> in all States and Kingdoms that acknowledge a ſubmiſsion to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Nay, that they might be the more ready to entertain theſe, and none but theſe they make no ſmall difficulty
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63736:6"/>to admit ordinary perſons to their Confeſſionaries, aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather at an Empire over the Conſciences of <hi>Princes,</hi> themſelves. By this means do they craftily dive into the deſignes, reſolutions and inclinations as well of <hi>Soveraigns</hi> as of <hi>Subjects,</hi> whereof they immediately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the Father <hi>Generall</hi> or his <hi>Aſſiſtants</hi> at <hi>Rome.</hi> Now to perceive and be ſatisfy'd what prejudice this muſt needs be to Princes, and what rubbes may be laid in their way when they imagine their affaires in a faire and ſecure poſture, a man needs no extraordinary mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſince <hi>ſecrecy</hi> is a proper and inſeparable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident which ſo attends the <hi>ſafety</hi> of a State, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it treacheries, circumventions, and ſo ruine muſt needs follow, it is not to be admir'd Princes ſhould be ſo ſecure againſt thoſe who diſcover their ſecrets, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing them as the moſt dangerous of their enemies. And whereas on the other ſide, the underſtanding of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Princes deſigns makes a man the more circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and more able to judge of his own condition, it is accordingly ordinary with them to be at vaſt charges in the maintenance of <hi>Ambaſſadours</hi> and <hi>Intelligencers;</hi> and yet are many times deceiv'd in the accompt they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from them.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> that is, their father-<hi>Generall,</hi> and his <hi>Aſſiſtants</hi> making their advantages as well of <hi>Confeſſions</hi> and <hi>Conſultations,</hi> whereof their Coreſpondents reſiding in all the chief Cities of the Chriſtian world, give them an account, as by the means of ſome other their Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, (of whom we ſhall have ſomething to ſay hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, are moſt faithfully and punctually inform'd of all determinations concluded even in the moſt ſecret Councells. Inſomuch, that they have a more particular knowledge of the power, poſſeſſions, expences and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Princes then the Princes themſelves have, and this without any other charge then that of the carriage of their Letters; which yet in <hi>Rome</hi> alone (as I have it from the relation of the Perſons employ'd about
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63736:6"/>thoſe affairs) amounts to ſeventy, eighty, nay, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a hundred Crownes of Gold to one <hi>Courrier</hi> or Meſſenger.</p>
            <p>Coming then by this means to know exactly the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of all Princes, they do not only do ill offices be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, but wound their reputation with their own ſubjects, depreſſing or advancing their concernments at their pleaſure. And that they can with the leſſe diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty do, for that by the ſame way of <hi>Confeſſions</hi> and <hi>Conſultations</hi> they ſerpent-like glide into the very ſecrets of the peoples ſoules, knowing who ſtand well affected to their Prince, who diſſatisfy'd and exaſperated. So that by theſe relations which they have of State-affairs they may eaſily ſow diſcord among Princes, raiſe thouſands of jealouſies, and by their inſight into the Subject's affections, raiſe commotions and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, making the perſon of the Prince contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible.</p>
            <p>From all which there can be no leſſe inferr'd, then that there is not any thing may prove more dangerous to the State, then that a Prince ſhould diſcover himſelf by Conſeſſion or otherwiſe, or that he ſhould permit any of his Confidents, Favorites, Secretaries, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours, or others his chief Miniſters ſhould make their Confeſſions to perſons that are perpetually ſifting mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of State, and making their advantages thereof to inſinuate into the favour of Princes. For there are men of other Religious <hi>Orders,</hi> comparable for life and Learning to any among the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> who may with the more ſafety be employ'd, out of conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that they attend nothing more then the cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivation of ſouls, and the Government of their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, which is a greater diſcovery then hath been made yet, the world is to take notice, that there are four ſorts or degrees of <hi>Jeſuits.</hi> The firſt <hi>degree</hi> is compos'd
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63736:7"/>of a number of ſecular perſons of both ſexes, that are taken or admitted to be of the Society, living accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly under a certain obedience, which themſelves call an <hi>implicite Obedience.</hi> Theſe are guided in all their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the advice of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> reſigning themſelves in all things abſolutely to their conduct. Thoſe that are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to this degree, are for the moſt part <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> and <hi>Gentlewomen,</hi> rich <hi>Widows,</hi> wealthy <hi>Citizens,</hi> and <hi>Merchants;</hi> which like a Plantation in the <hi>Indies,</hi> bring in to the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> a very vaſt revenue of Gold and Silver. Of this kind are thoſe Women, who in <hi>Italy,</hi> are called <hi>Chettine,</hi> who are by the ſubtill perſwaſions of the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> induced to forſake the world, when in the mean time they take a care to disburthen them of their Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, apparrell, and ornaments, houſhold ſtoffe, and in a word, if there be any thing, of their eſtates of great value.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> degree conſiſts of men alone, and that cheequer'd as well with Prieſts as Laywen, yet ſuch as live wholly after a ſecular way, being not oblig'd to a regular life. Theſe are a ſort of people who by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation and recommendations of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eep into Penſions, Abbeys, Benefices and other revenues; but they vow to put on the habit of the Society, when ever it ſhall pleaſe the Father <hi>General</hi> to require it of them, for which reaſon they are called Jeſuits in <hi>Voto;</hi> and of the labours of theſe men, the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> make no ſmall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages in order to the erection, and ſettlement of their <hi>Monarchy.</hi> For they maintain in all Kingdoms and Provinces in all Princes Courts &amp; Palaces of Great-men ſuch of this degree <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they know how to make uſe of; as ſhall be further diſcovered in the ſeventh point of this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>third</hi> ſort of <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are theſe who are reſident in Monaſteries. Theſe are either Prieſts, Clerks or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, who may at the pleaſure of the Father <hi>General.</hi> be diſpens'd with, as to any thing relating to their Proſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, though of themſelves they have no power to leave
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63736:7"/>it. And theſe being ſuch as have no Office of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the Community, do for the moſt part ſimply obey in any thing they are put upon by the Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors.</p>
            <p>The <hi>fourth</hi> ſort is that of Politick <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> to whom is committed the management of the Affairs of <hi>Religion,</hi> and the regulation of the <hi>Society.</hi> And theſe are they, who being tempted by the Devill with the ſame tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that Chriſt had in the Goſpel, <hi>viz. All theſe things will I give thee,</hi> have taken the Tempter at his word. Upon which account it is, that they ſo much endeavour to reduce their <hi>Society</hi> to an abſolute <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and to place the head thereof at <hi>Rome,</hi> the centre where all the principall affairs of the Chriſtian world meet. There conſtantly reſideth the grand <hi>Monarch</hi> of theſe <hi>Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> (their Father <hi>General</hi>) with a great number of others of the ſame Inſtitution, who having receiv'd informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from their Spies of all ſuch weighty and important buſineſſes as are to be canvaſs'd in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> they preſently call a Councell, and having in the firſt place taken order to ſecure their own intereſts, every one in particular makes it his buſineſſe to go their cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit through the Courts of <hi>Cardinals, Prelates</hi> and <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours.</hi> Their buſineſſe with theſe is cunningly to ſhiſt their diſcourſe to ſomething relating to the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe then in hand, or shortly to come upon the ſtage, repreſenting it to them after what manner they pleaſe, ſo diſguiſing it, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt for their intereſt, ſo far as if need be, to ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> black in ſtead of white. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the firſt repreſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons of a buſineſſe made by men pretending to ſincerity and the ſtrictneſſe of a Religious life cannot but make the more remarkable in preſſion in the mind of him that they are addreſt to, the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is, that Affaires of very great importance treated by the Ambaſſadors of Princes, and other grave perſons, in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> have not carried on with the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe expeſted by the Princes therein concern'd meerly through the ſycophancy of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> who by their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63736:8"/>adulterate relations had ſo ſhuffled things, that there was but little credit left for what might be alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Ambaſſadors and other Agents employ'd therein.</p>
            <p>The ſame tricks they play the Prelates of <hi>Rome,</hi> they alſo put upon other Princes, either by themſelves, or by the means of their Penſionary <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> out of <hi>Rome.</hi> So that it may well be concluded, that the greateſt part of what is done all over the Chriſtian world, paſſes through the hands of the <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> and thoſe only take effect, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which they make no oppoſition. Stupendious and inexpreſſible are the artifices and inſinuations they make uſe of in this kind, which though it is impoſſible for me to decypher, yet may it not haply be ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure to thoſe Princes, who ſhall ſeriouſly obſerve the ſlight Character I have here given of them. For if they do, they preſently reflect on the things that are paſt, and as they muſt needs be more and more convinc'd of the truth of my diſcourſe, the more they call to mind with what Art things have been handled, ſo will it ſtill fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them in the diſcovery of what ſeem'd ſo ſtrange and marvellous to them. Nay, not content with this cloſe artifice, whereby they inſenſibly thruſt themſelves into the Affaires of the world, out of a confidence that it is the only means to attain that Monarchicall Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendency at which they aime, they were ſo inſolent as to petition Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> XIII. "That for the time to come he would publickly countenance their Project. And thence taking occaſion to commend it to him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of the publick good of the Church, they required that he would command all his Legates and Apoſtolicall Nuncio's to take to them every one for his Companion and confident, ſome <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> by whoſe Counſell he ſhould be governed in all his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, by theſe crafty inſinuations, and their infight into Affairs of publick concernment, the moſt eminent among the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have gain'd the love of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63736:8"/>Princes, as well <hi>Temporall</hi> as <hi>Spirituall,</hi> whom they have the confidence to perſwade that they have ſaid and done many things for their advantage; and this proceeding of theirs is the Damme of two very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable inconveniences. The firſt is, that, abuſing the favour and friendſhip which the Princes had for them, they have made no difficulty to diſguſt many private, though otherwiſe rich and Noble Families, uſurping the wealth of Widowes, though with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of their Retinue and Relations to extreme miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: enticing, to embrace their Inſtitution, and to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent their Schools, perſons of the nobleſt and moſt hopefull Inclination, who yet if they prov'd unfit for the employments they deſign'd them for, were under ſome pretence or other diſmiſs'd the Society, which though it parted from their perſons, yet could not be got to part with their Eſtates. And while they did thus, they abſolutely excluded the poor from their Schooles, forgetting quite the pious proviſions for ſuch of their Founder <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and the intentions of thoſe patrons of theirs, who endowed them with large Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues, not that they ſhould mind only their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, but be ſerviceable to the Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> Inconvenience is, that theſe <hi>Jeſuits</hi> omit no occaſion whereby they would make the world ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the familiarity and influence which they have over Princes, making the people, by their crafty repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations of it, look thereon as through a magnifying glaſſe, to the end they may ingratiate themſelves with their <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and ſo bring things about, that all that ſtand in need of favour may make their applications to them. Thus they ſtick not to make their braggs, that it is in their power to make <hi>Cardinals, Nuncio's, Governours</hi> of Places and other officers of the publick. Nay, ſome of them have roundly ſtood upon't, that <hi>their General could do more then the Pope himſelf</hi> Others have added that <hi>it is better to be of that</hi> Order <hi>which makes</hi> Cardinals, <hi>then to be a Cardinal.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:63736:9"/>Theſe, and ſuch like expreſſions of their inſupportable inſolence are obvious to all that converſe with them.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, having thus laid the foundation of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terloping into State aſtaires, the firſt thing they build upon it, is a pretence of power to raiſe or ruine whom they pleaſe. And indeed making <hi>Religion</hi> a meer ſtalk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing horſe to their own <hi>Reputation,</hi> they many times ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect their deſignes. But when they recommend any man to the Prince in order to advancement, they never make choice of the moſt fit and deſerving, but rather, if any ſuch appear, oppoſe him, eſpecially if he be one they know to be no favourer of them. So that they make it their deſign to preferre thoſe that are likely to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance their intereſt, never minding his good affection to the Prince or his capacity to go through the Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he is advanced to: whereof the conſequences are, to the Prince, <hi>Exaſperation</hi> at his being eluded, to the people <hi>diſguſt</hi> and <hi>inſurrections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, as the Maſter of a Galley, when he finds the wind faire for his voyage, with once whiſtling, makes the ſlaves handle their Oares, and ſet the Veſſell to her full ſpeed: ſo when in the Aſſemblyes and conſultations (which theſe Fathers continually hold by their <hi>Generall</hi> and his <hi>Aſſistants</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi>) it is concluded, that it makes for their advantage, that ſuch a perſon ſhould be promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to dignity, the Father-Generall ſignifies ſo much to thoſe that reſide elſewhere, and all thoſe immeditely joyn together, and with united forces bring him to the honour intended him. Which having gotten, he were an inſufferable example of <hi>Ingratitude,</hi> if he ſhould not afterwards indeavour to ſerve the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> with a zale ſuitable to that of theirs, when they advanc'd him. And hence indeed does it proceed that ſuch a man, nay, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch men (for it is not to be imagin'd the dependants on the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> of this kind are few) acknowledging themſelves more oblig'd to the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> then to their <hi>Prince,</hi> for the honour and greatneſs they are rais'd to,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63736:9"/>do accordingly ſerve the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> with farr greater affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction then they do the <hi>Prince</hi> himſelf. Thus are their Princes fool'd and deluded by them, when imagining they have got a truſty ſervant, they have only made way for a Spie of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> who only make their advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of him, to the great prejudice of the <hi>Prince</hi> that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced him.</p>
            <p>There are many examples might be brought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the preſent diſcourſe; but indeed it needs not; daily experience, and the generall report are ſufficient atteſtations of the truth delivered. To avoid tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe therefore, I ſhall conclude this point, ſaying, that this haply is the cauſe why the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are wont to call their way of Religion, <hi>A Grand Monarchy;</hi> as if they governed all Princes and their Miniſters at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Nor is it long ſince, that one of the chief among them, being to treat publickly with an Illuſtrious Prince in the name of the <hi>Society,</hi> began with theſe words full of arrogance, and grounded upon a conceit of their Monarchy; <hi>Our Society hath alwayes maintained good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence with your Grace, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, thoſe Fathers make a great ſtir to let the world know, that all thoſe that are any way in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of their Prince, were ſometimes Creatures of theirs, and are oblig'd for their advancement to them. Hence it muſt follow, that they have a greater com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the ſubjects affections then the Prince himſelf, upon whom this muſt needs bring great inconvenieni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. For it is in the firſt place an <hi>affront</hi> to the <hi>publick</hi> Intereſt, that a ſort of <hi>Religious</hi> Perſons, that pretend to have abjur'd all commerce with the things of this world, yet ſo ambitious and politick, ſhould have ſuch an influence over Miniſters of State, that when ever it pleaſes them, they can cauſe Treaſons and inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Secondly, it is dangerous, ſince that by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of the Miniſters their Adherents, they induce into the <hi>Princes</hi> ſervice for <hi>Counſellors</hi> or <hi>Secretaries</hi> ſome of the Jeſuits <hi>in Voto,</hi> of whom mention is made
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63736:10"/>before, and theſe again perſwade the Prince to take ſome <hi>Jeſuit</hi> for his <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> or Chaplaine. Thus do they all combine together to ſerve as Intelligencers to the Father <hi>General,</hi> to whom they give an exact account of all the <hi>tranſactions</hi> of the moſt <hi>ſecret</hi> Councells. Whence it comes, that many times we ſee deſignes prevented, and ſecrets of the greateſt importance di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcovered, and yet things are carried ſo cunningly, that no man can fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en on the true Author, but it common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happens, that the greateſt ſuſpition lies on thoſe that are moſt innocent.</p>
            <p>Eightly, 'Tis a common obſervation, that Subjects are naturally much given to imitate and comply with the inclinations of their Prince. In like manner thoſe, who give obedience to their Father <hi>Generall,</hi> percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that his thoughts are wholly taken up with matters of State, as indeavouring by that means to improve and enrich their Society, do alſo apply themſelves that way; and thereupon making uſe of their Relations and friends, would penetrate into the very hearts of Princes, ſo to diſcover their moſt ſecret deſigns, only to betray them to the <hi>Aſſiſtants</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> or the Father <hi>Generall;</hi> out of a confidence, by that means, to get into their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and be advanc'd into ſome employment, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they could never have expected. For among them, none are ever preferr'd to any Office of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and truſt, but only thoſe whom they have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd moſt inclined to advance their Society to that height of Greatneſſe whereto they aſpire, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently none but ſuch as are known to be able and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert in the management of State affairs.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, as from divers <hi>Flowers</hi> and <hi>Herbs,</hi> by the means of an Alembick, a man may extract ſuch an oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as ſhall have the Vertue to heal a mortall wound; and as from ſeveral <hi>bloſſomes</hi> Bees draw that which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>words becomes honey: ſo theſe <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> from the infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble account which they have of all Princes affaires, and of all the emergencies of every State, do by the power
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63736:10"/>of their diſcourſe, extract from them what makes for their own advantage, which is in ſome meaſure a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for their inſatiable avarice and ambition. And they are excellent Maſters in a certain Art, unknown to others, whereby they effect their deſignes equally from other mens either good or ill; but more often from their misfortunes then happineſſe.</p>
            <p>Nor is it unuſuall with them to enſnare the unwary Prince into whoſe ſecrets they have dived, propoſing to him, that they have in their hands the onely excellent means to make him maſter of his deſires. But when by theſe pretences they have made their advantages of him, if it do but come into their imagination that the ſpreading greatneſſe of that Prince may one day prove prejudiciall to them, they do, as Lawyers in their cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, prolong the ſucceſſe of the buſineſſe what lyes in their power; till at laſt with ſtrange juggling, and an imperceptible kind of Legerdemaine they utterly ruine thoſe deſignes to which they had given birth.</p>
            <p>The Ligue of France treated and concluded by them, they not long after baſely renounc'd all medling with, when they ſaw things proſper on the Kings ſide: and <hi>England,</hi> ſo often promiſed by them to the Spany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, yet in ſuch manner performed, ſo confirms the preſent diſcourſe, that there needs no further proof.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, from what hath been already alledged, it neceſſarily follows, that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have no ſincere af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection towards any Prince whatſoever, either tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or ſpirituall, but onely comply with them ſo farre as ſtands with their own convenience and advantage.</p>
            <p>Nay, it may be yet further inferr'd, that no Prince, much leſſe any Prelates of an inferiour degree can make any effectuall uſe of them, becauſe they ſeem, at the ſame time to be equally affected to all, complying with the <hi>French</hi> as if they were <hi>French,</hi> with the <hi>Spanyards</hi> as if they were <hi>Spanyards,</hi> and ſo with all others, as the occaſion requires; from all which the onely rule of their <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> is, to <hi>exact</hi> their own profit and accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63736:11"/>They never regard the prejudice of one more then another, and thence it comes that thoſe enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, wherein they have intermedled, have ſeldome ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded well, becauſe they are no further embarqu'd therein then their own intereſt adviſes them. And as to this particular, the artifices they uſe are notorious; ſome of them pretending great inclinations for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of <hi>France,</hi> others of <hi>Spain,</hi> others of the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> and others of ſome other Princes of whom they deſire to be favoured.</p>
            <p>And if any of theſe Princes be deſirous to make uſe of ſome <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> whom he imagines to be very much his Friend, he immediately acquaints the F. <hi>Generall</hi> by Letter with the buſineſſe which he hath to treat, and expects his Anſwer, together with order what he ſhall do, and ſuitably to the commands he receives, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds in his affair. Never regarding whether that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>Generall</hi> be conformable to the intention of the <hi>Prince,</hi> who hath entruſted him with the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that buſineſſe. But ſo the <hi>Society</hi> be ſerved and comply'd with, he matters not what diſſervice it may be to the <hi>Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this may be added, that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> underſtanding the ſeverall intereſts of all Princes, and being acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all things daily treated in ſecret Councels, thoſe who pretend an inclination for <hi>France</hi> propound to the King and his principall Miniſters certain Memorialls of State and important conſiderations ſent to them from their politick Fathers at <hi>Rome.</hi> On the other ſide thoſe who pretend to hold with the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> do juſt the ſame with them, and ſo with the reſt. From which carriage of theirs ariſeth this miſchief, that it cauſes ſuch diſtruſts in the hearts of Chriſtian Princes, that they cannot credit one the other; which is a great hindrance to the publick peace, and the univerſall well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of Chriſtendome. Beſides, this diffidence of theirs is that which makes it ſo difficult a thing to conclude a league againſt the common enemy, and the precious
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63736:11"/>enjoyments of peace to be of ſo little value among Princes.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, with theſe circumventing devices, though they have ſo opened the eyes of the world, and ſo ſharpened mens wits in matter of State that they are notorious to all, yet, even at this very day, to the great prejudice of the Church, they are wholly taken up with matters of policy, and ballance all their actions according to their worldly and ſelfiſh concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>But that theſe Jeſuiticall <hi>Myſteries</hi> and <hi>Stratagems</hi> may be made yet more manifeſt, I cannot here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale the means whereby they inveigle Princes to their party. There are ſome years now paſt, ſince one of theſe Fathers, called Father <hi>Parſons,</hi> the Aſſiſtant of <hi>England,</hi> wrote a book againſt the ſucceſſion of the King of <hi>Scotland</hi> to the crown of <hi>England;</hi> And another Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſame Society called <hi>Crittonius,</hi> with ſome others, in a Book which they wrote, defended the Title of the King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> oppoſing the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Father <hi>Parſons,</hi> and pretending to be at difference among themſelves. But the truth, was, that all was cunningly contriv'd and carryed on by the command of their Father <hi>Generall,</hi> onely out of this deſign, that whoſoever ſhould ſucceed in the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> they might have an excellent argument to work in him a great good opinion of their Society, and ſo as much as may be make their advantages of him.</p>
            <p>What more pertinent example can we deſire to ſhew that Princes and their intereſts are the objects of all Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiticall actions and determinations, and conſequently, to make good their own aſſertion, <hi>That their Society is a grand Monarchy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, that this truth may alſo be made manifeſt. <hi>That the Jeſuits regard not whether they pleaſe or diſpleaſe any Prince when their own commedity lyes at the stake;</hi> though the experience of infinite things paſt make it as clear as the Sun, yet the particular inſtance I ſhall
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63736:12"/>now adde wil make it ſomewhat the more conſpicuous.</p>
            <p>There is not any perſon in the world whom they are more bound to ſerve, or indeed, for whom they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves pretend greater ſubmiſſion, then the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> were it not for other particular reaſons, but out of a conſideration only of the ſolemn <hi>vow</hi> they make to obey him. Yet when <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> would have brought in ſomething of reformation amongſt theſe Fathers, by reducing them to a performance of their duty in the <hi>Quire,</hi> they ſubmiſſively refuſed to obey him, as conceiving it a notorious prejudice to their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety to be reduced to any thing ſuitable to the practiſe of other Monkes. And for thoſe few among them that conſcientiouſly did comply with the Popes pleaſure, they were ever afterwards called by way of deriſion <hi>Quintini,</hi> and made ſo contemptible that never any of them could be admitted to the leaſt preferment among them.</p>
            <p>After the ſame manner did they oppoſe glorious S <hi>Charles.</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Millaine,</hi> when in the quality of Legate <hi>à latere</hi> to his Holineſſe, he endeavoured to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to Religious diſcipline.</p>
            <p>But to what end do I mention theſe, when they think it a ſcorn to ſubmit to the ſacred Canons themſelves, but contrary to the proviſions made therein make mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe of <hi>Jewels, Rubies,</hi> and <hi>Diamends</hi> which they trade to the Indies for. Nor is that opinion altogether groundleſſe, that the greateſt part of the precious ſtones ſold in <hi>Venice</hi> belong to the <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> ſince the report took its firſt riſe from their own <hi>Agents</hi> and <hi>Brokers</hi> whom they employ'd in the ſale of them.</p>
            <p>But that they are no faithfull Servants to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> what ever they pretend, I need onely the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of thoſe Fathers who for no mean de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault were called by proceſſe to <hi>Rome.</hi> I neither can, nor would, if I could, name them; nor am I much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to wade any farther into this buſineſſe, partly to avoid the bringing of any Prince upon the ſtage that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63736:12"/>might take offence at my diſcourſe (it being my deſire to pleaſe all, and not to diſoblige any) and partly that it might not be ſaid I were guilty of an humour to inveigh againſt the <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> my purpoſe only having been to give a ſhort and plain account of their courſes and cuſtomes.</p>
            <p>For as it many times happens, that we ſee a perſon afflicted with ſome grievous infirmity, betraying the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of his ſufferings by ſuch lamentations and cryes as reach heaven it ſelf; and it is apparent to every one that the man ſuffers no ſmall torment, yet there is not any able to diſcern the originall cauſe of his indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: So the world is full of complaints againſt the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits,</hi> ſome for being perſecuted by them, others for being treacherouſly ſerved by them, yet the miſchief ſtill remains among us. Nor is the cauſe thereof eaſily diſcovered, though it is conceived it does not proceed from any thing ſo much as from that prodigious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determinate deſire which they have ſtill to encreaſe their power. This is the apple of their eye, which if it be but ever ſo little touched, they make no difficulty to diſguſt any man whatſoever, to circumvent and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reach Princes, to oppreſſe the poor, to force Widdows out of their eſtates, to ruine whole Nations, nay many times by their interloping into affairs of publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment to raiſe jealouſies and diſſatisfactions among Chriſtian Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>Now as there would happen a great inconvenience, if that part which according to the deſigne of Nature was laſt formed as an inſtrument to ſerve the reſt that for their precedency are the more noble, and ſhould attract unto it ſelf all the pureſt blood and vitall ſpirits, for it were the way to bring the whole to deſtruction. So is it no leſſe inconvenient, that the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> an Inſtitution lately graffed into the body of the <hi>Church</hi> to be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall, as they then ſelves pretend, in the converſion of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and the reduction of <hi>Sinners</hi> into the ways of <hi>Repentance,</hi> ſhould graſp into their power, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume upon the management of all the moſt weighty
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63736:13"/>and important affaires of <hi>Prelates</hi> and <hi>Princes,</hi> drawing from them the very life and ſpirits of their intereſts, to make their own advantages thereof. From this ſource ſprings all publick and private diſturbances, many are depreſſed, who, were their worth conſider'd, ſhould be exalted, many advanc'd who were more deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trod under foot, with thouſands of other inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences conſequent thereto.</p>
            <p>Many reaſons might be produc'd, drawn from expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience it ſelf, to make it apparent what an inſatiable am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have to encreaſe ſtill more and more in greatneſſe. It ſhall therefore ſuffice to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare out of the words of Father <hi>Parſons,</hi> one of the Society, as they may be found in a book of his which he writ in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> entituled, <hi>The Reformation of England.</hi> Having in the firſt place blamed Cardinall <hi>Pool,</hi> and then taken notice of many defects and imperfections in the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> he concludes, <hi>That when</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>ſhould returne to the</hi> Roman <hi>Catholick faith, He would reduce it to the forme and ſtate of the Primitive Church, making common all Eccleſiaſticall Goods, and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gning the overſight thereof, unto ſeven</hi> Savii, <hi>or wiſe men who ſhould be</hi> Jeſuits <hi>and were to make diſtribution of the ſame as they ſhould think convenient.</hi> He further thinks it fit, under a grievous penalty, <hi>to forbid all Religious perſons of what</hi> Order <hi>ſoever to return into</hi> England <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their</hi> Licence, <hi>reſolving that none ſhould be entertained there, but thoſe that were to be maintained by Alms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, as it oft falls out that <hi>Self-love</hi> ſo blinds the wifeſt man that he betrayes his imprudence to all the world, ſo is that a moſt ridiculous paſſage which the ſame Father adds in the place before cited, <hi>When Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall once be reduced to the true Faith, it will not be convenient that the Popes (at leaſt for five years ſpace) ſhould expect any advantage from the Eccleſiaſticall Benefices of this Kingdome; but remit all into the hands of thoſe ſeven</hi> Savii, <hi>who ſhould diſpoſe of them as they conceived beſt for the good of the Church.</hi> This being his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63736:13"/>deſign, that, the firſt five years being paſt, by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther invention (whereof they are very full) they would get the ſame priviledge confirmed to them for five more, and ſo onward, till they had utterly excluded his Holineſſe from having any thing to do in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what more lively repreſentation can there be made of the avarice and ambition of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the deſire they have to erect an abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy? Who ſees not with what ſlights they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to promote their own Intereſt, not caring who are made happy, who unhappy, ſo their concernments be ſecured. What ſhould I ſay more of them? Did they not, in the time of <hi>Gregory</hi> the thirteenth, make it there requeſt that they might be inveſted of all the Pariſh-Churches in <hi>Rome?</hi> that they might there lay the foundations of their <hi>Monarchy?</hi> and what they could not get in <hi>Rome,</hi> have they not at length obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>England,</hi> where not long ſince they have choſen an <hi>Arch-Prieſt,</hi> one of the <hi>Jeſuits in Voto,</hi> who inſtead of protecting the Clergy, like a ravenous wolf perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes all ſuch Prieſts as have no dependance on the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits worrying them even to exaſperation and deſpair, and depriving them (under a great penalty) of mutuall communication. To which may be added their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy to become <hi>Jeſuits in Voto,</hi> not admitting any one into their Colledges, who hath not made ſome engagement to be <hi>a Jeſuit.</hi> So that when that Kingdome ſhall returne to the ancient Faith, it will give a fair beginning to an abſolute <hi>Jeſuiticall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerchy,</hi> when all the Eccleſiaſticall Revenues, all the Abbeyes, Benefices, Biſhopticks, Arch-Prieſtſhips and other dignities ſhall be altogether at the diſpoſall of the <hi>Jeſuits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are many other things I might have inſiſted on, as the pretentions they make concerning other mens eſtates; as alſo how jealous they are of their wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, and deſirous of their proſperity. What a ſly way is that they have to infinuate into the favour of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63736:14"/>by perſuading them that their Subjects are more inclined to the <hi>Society</hi> in matters of devotion, then to any other <hi>Order</hi> or Religious <hi>Inſtitution;</hi> and what muſt needs be conſequent thereto, that they, of all men, are the moſt ſit and able to make them well affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Prince. Such obvious things as theſe, I leave to every mans particular obſervation; and with <hi>foure</hi> brief conſiderations conclude the preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> that men of ſuch turbulent ſpirits, and ſuch reaching deſignes muſt withall be Lovers of Novelty, ever ſearching for it, ever begetting it; becauſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome new raiſed motions, it were impoſſible they ſhould attain their ends. Whence it is to be inferr'd, that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> cannot be helpfull to any Prince that either loves Peace or endeavours the preſervation of his own eſtate, ſince they are more likely to prove the occaſions of much diſtraction and diſturbance, nay to endanger the loſſe of his eſtate, if he favour not their party, or be not in ſome things guided by their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> be it taken into ſerious conſideration, if theſe men, who though they have not yet any tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall juriſdiction, are able by their flickling and bandy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to occaſion ſo great and prodigious diſturbances in the world, what can we imagine they would not do, if it ſhould happen that one of them were created <hi>Pope?</hi> No queſtion but he would in the firſt place, fill up the Conſiſtory with <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and by that means perpetuate the <hi>Papacy</hi> in the <hi>Society.</hi> And then making advantage of their inſight and intereſt in State affaires, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the arme and power of the <hi>Pope</hi> they would be in a capacity to endanger the eſtates of many Princes, eſpecially thoſe that are their Neighbours and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> one of them being once gotten in the <hi>chair,</hi> it would be the deſign of that <hi>Pope</hi> (if he could by any means effect it) to give the <hi>Society</hi> poſſeſſion of ſome
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63736:14"/>place of impertance or temporall juriſdiction, by the advantages whereof they would in proceſſe of time make way for thouſands of other deſignes, which they could never compaſſe, but with the prejudice of other <hi>Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> when the Conſiſtory ſhall be once entirely <hi>Jeſuited,</hi> the whole Patrimony of Chriſt would be at their diſpoſall; whereof this would be the conſequence, that as one in a dropfie, the more he drinks, the more thirſty he is, ſo their Ambition, encreaſing proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to their greatneſſe, would occaſion a world of tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult and trouble. Now, ſince there is nothing more ſubject to change then matters of State, it would be the aime of theſe Fathers, with all their power and policy, to alter the courſe of affaires, that they might at length introduce the forme and project of their own Government, and by that means abſolutely <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monarchize</hi> themſelves. It hath been long in their heads to cajoll into the <hi>Society</hi> the ſonne of ſome Soveraigne Prince, who ſhould be drawn in to make an abſolute reſignation of his eſtate and Dominions to them. And this they had long ſince effected, if ſome others ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſtrict notice of their deſigne, had not prevented them. But had they once made that ſtep, no doubt, but the next would have been to become Patrones of the State <hi>Eccleſiasticall;</hi> and being a ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple very ſubtle and much inclined to plots, they would afterwards have found thouſands of wayes how to enlarge it. Thus would they not have omitted any thing to put their projects in execution; and if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe would have done it, the very jealouſies which they would have raiſed in the minds of their neighbour Princes would have turned not a little to their advantage.</p>
            <p>From all that hath been ſaid, it ſeems to follow as a thing moſt neceſſary, that for the preſervation of the publick peace, the tranquillity of all States, the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the Church, and the generall good of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63736:15"/>whole world, <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, together with other <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> ſhould ſet bounds and limits to this <hi>Society,</hi> whoſe deſires are ſo extremely inordinate, leſt haply that come to paſſe which was anciently effected by the <hi>Daui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di</hi> (whoſe courſes the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> ſeem to imitate) who were not deſtroyed till the time of <hi>Claudius</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</p>
            <p>And if ever I am commanded to write my opinion concerning an opportune remedy for the reformation of theſe Fathers, without any prejudice or diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them, nay to their very great advantage (as wiſhing them rather Monarchs of Souls, which are the riches of Chriſt, then of the World or the enjoyments thereof, that are nothing but vileneſſe and dung) I ſhall be ready to do it with <hi>charity,</hi> and according to the beſt of my skill, as it ſhall pleaſe God to enable me.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:63736:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
